<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
                      "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd"
>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>MEME-ChIP Tutorial</title>
    <link href="./meme-suite.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" />
  </head>
  <body>
    <div id="main">
      <script src="./meme-suite-logo.js" type="text/javascript">></script>
      <h1>MEME-ChIP Tutorial</h1>

      <p>
        <h2>Purpose</h2>
      </p>

      <p>
	MEME-ChIP performs several motif analysis steps on a set of
	DNA sequences that you provide.  It is especially appropriate
	for analyzing the bound genomic regions identified in a transcription factor (TF) 
	ChIP-seq experiment.
	MEME-ChIP can 1) discover novel DNA-binding motifs, 2) analyze them
	for similarity to known binding motifs, 3) visualize the arrangement
	of the predicted motif sites in your input sequences, 4) detect
	very subtly enriched known motifs in your sequences, and 5) provide
	an estimate of the amount of binding of each novel motif to each
	of your sequences.
      </p>
      <p>
	You provide MEME-ChIP with a set of sequences in FASTA format.
	Ideally the sequences are about 100 base-pairs long and
	enriched for motifs.  The immediate regions around individual ChIP-seq
	"peaks" from a transcription factor (TF) ChIP-seq experiment
	are ideal.  <b>There is no limit on the number of sequences
	you provide, and they may be longer (or shorter) than 100 base-pairs
	if you desire.</b>  (The suggested 100 base-pair size is based on the typical
	resolution of ChIP-seq peaks.)  We recommend that you 
	"repeat mask" your sequences, replacing repeat regions to the "N" character.
      </p>

      <p>
	The overall purpose of MEME-ChIP is to provide you with a
	number of investigations of your sequences without having to
	configure a number of tools separately. These investigations are:
	<ol>
	  <li><i>Ab initio</i> motif discovery &#x2013; for which
	    we provide two different analyses, using MEME and DREME:
	    <ul>
	      <li>MEME is good for finding your ChIPed TF's motif,
		and can find wide motifs corresponding to complexes
	      </li>
	      <li>DREME is good for finding shorter monomeric motifs
		and cofactors
	      </li>
	    </ul>
	  </li>
	  <li>Comparison to known motifs &#x2013; TOMTOM compares motifs
	    found in your sequences by one of our <i>ab initio</i>
	    tools to known motifs in a database.
	  </li>
	  <li>Visualization of motifs in the input sequences &#x2013;
	    MAST shows you where motifs found using an <i>ab initio</i>
	    approach match the sequences
	  </li>
	  <li>Estimation of binding affinity of input sequences to
	    each motif &#x2013; AMA measures how strongly a motif
	    is associated with each sequence.
	  </li>
	  <li>Motif enrichment analysis &#x2013; AME discovers 
	    subtly enriched <i>known</i> binding motifs in your
	    input sequences
	  </li>
	</ol>
      </p>

      <p>
      <h2>Biological questions you can address using MEME-ChIP</h2>
	<ul>
	  <li>What does a binding site for the ChIPed TF look like?
	  MEME and DREME allow you to answer this question.</li>
	  <li>Is binding a simple event or is there a complex involved in
	  binding? If the latter, MEME will likely find significantly longer
	  motifs than DREME.</li>
	  <li>Does binding involve cofactors? If so, DREME will likely find
	  more than one motif with a low <i>p-</i>value.</li>
	  <li>Are there binding sites for TFs whose motifs are already
	  known? AME answers this question by finding known motifs that
	  are enriched in your sequences.</li>
	  <li>Are any found motifs similar to known motifs? TOMTOM answers
	  this question by comparing found motifs with a database
	  of known motifs.</li>
	</ul>
      </p>

      <h2>MEME-ChIP Examples</h2>
      <p>
	We supply data to allow you to run a complete example, based on
	sequences from a ChIP-seq experiment (Klf1, mouse); you may also
	wish to study the outputs from a different example which
	<a href="examples/memechip_example_output_files/index.html">we provide</a>
	(SCL, also known as Tal1), and compare those outputs
	with those you obtain from the Klf1 example.
      </p>
      <p>
	To see how the system works, try submitting the supplied Klf1
	sample.  Below the button for submitting a file, locate the
	link to &#8220;<b>Sample DNA Input Sequences</b>&#8221;. Click
	on the link, copy the sequence data, use the web
	browser's <b>back</b> button to go back to the data form, and
	paste the sequences into the box provided below the text
	&#8220;<b>the actual sequences here (Sample DNA Input
	Sequences):</b>&#8221;. This example has 945 sequences, just
	enough to get answers of reasonably high significance, and to
	exercise all the features of the web service. Do no change any
	of the settings, and click <b>Start search</b> at the bottom
	of the form.  You should see confirmation that your job has
	been submitted. If you click the link next to the words
	&#8220;<b>You can view your job results at:</b>&#8221;, and
	refresh the screen every now and then, you will see a summary
	of your results in about an hour. If you have other things to
	do, don't worry if you have to close your web browser and go
	away: you will receive an email echoing the confirmation page,
	that includes directing you to the results. The primary motif
	should be a CACC motif, and GATA should feature as a secondary
	motif. SCL (also called TAL1) may also be associated with this
	data set, though harder to find.
      </p>
      <p>
	Once outputs are available, here are some options open to you:
      </p>
	<ul>
	  <li>
	    Look at MEME's output report. The first motif is
	    likely to be a reasonable representation of the binding
	    site for the main TF of interest. Go back to the
	    report summary page, and look at the outputs from MAST.
	    You should see the MEME motifs represented in most
	    sequences, sometimes more than once per sequence.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Look at DREME's output report. You should find a longer
	    list of motifs than MEME found. Even if MEME found longer
	    motifs than DREME did, see if the DREME motifs, especially
	    those with lowest <i>p</i>-values, look like truncated
	    versions of any motifs MEME found.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Look at TOMTOM's output, which contains known motifs that
	    are most similar to the motifs DREME found. You will also
	    find logos there representing DREME's found motifs. Are
	    the motifs in known databases that are most similar (near
	    the top of this list for each DREME motif submitted to
	    TOMTOM) plausible? With our example, you should expect to
	    find Klf4 near the top of the CACC motifs, and several
	    GATA motifs. Do you see anything suggesting an SCL (TAL1)
	    binding site? As an additional step, go back to the MEME
	    output. Under each logo, at the start of the information
	    for that motif, you should find a button to submit that
	    motif to TOMTOM.  Try this as well.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Look at AME's output. Compare the motifs with low <i>p</i>-values
	    with those found by MEME and DREME. Do you find anything unexpected,
	    or is anything you expect to find missing?
	  </li>
<!--
	  <li>
	    Finally, look at the outputs from SpaMo. Compare secondary
	    motifs particularly with those found by DREME and AME. Do you
	    find any evidence that any of these motifs are preferentially
	    found with a fixed offset from the primary motif?
	    <b>FIXME: not yet implemented</b>.
	  </li>
-->
	</ul>
	<p>
	Once you have this information, you are in a position to start
	reasoning about the motifs you have found. Here are some
	examples of questions you may ask. Is the primary motif found
	by MEME and DREME essentially the same? Is that primary motif
	a known motif for the primary transcription factor, or similar
	to such a known motif? Does AME find a known motif similar to
	the primary motif with one of AME's lowest
	<i>p</i>-values? Are any known motifs found by AME likely to be cofactors?
	How do secondary motifs identified by MEME and DREME compare? How <!--  and SpaMo -->
	low are the <i>p</i>-values of theses secondary motifs as found by these
	tools? In the event that all the tools find consistent results, this increases
	your confidence that you have found a motif or motifs consistent with your
	input sequences. If the tools find inconsistent results, you need to
	investigate further to understand the cause or causes of the inconsistency.
      </p>

	<p>
	  Once you have worked through this example, study the description below
	  of the tools we use here, and the outputs produced for more insight into
	  how to construct your own examples. To get some idea of how time scales
	  up, MEME takes about 4 times as long every time you double the size
	  of the data (total number of bases in the sequences). Once you submit
	  more than 600 sequences, time for the other tools increases linearly,
	  so for very large examples, much larger than 600 sequences, you should
	  expect run time to double if you double the size of your input. However,
	  for runs of a few thousand sequences, most of the run time will be taken
	  by MEME, even though we limit MEME to 600 sequences.
	</p>

      <h2>Tools used by MEME-ChIP</h2>

      <ul>
	<li>
        <a href="../meme-intro.html"><b>MEME</b></a> finds motifs in DNA and
	protein sequences (here, we only process DNA sequences). MEME
	is able to find relatively long motifs, and hence does a good
	job of finding motifs characteristic of multi-protein complexes.
      </li>

      <li>
        <a href="../mast-intro.html"><b>MAST</b></a> identifies locations in a
	set of sequences where a given set of motifs has a
	statistically significant match to such locations, indicating
	the site where each motif has such a match. We generally use
	MAST as a follow-up step to running MEME to show where the
	motifs MEME has found may have sites in the sequences.
      </li>

      <li>
	<a href="ama.html"><b>AMA</b></a> scores a motif against each
	DNA sequence
      </li>

<!--
      <li>
        <b>SpaMo</b> finds over-represented motifs at a fixed spacing from
	a given motif. SpaMo is useful for finding cofactors. <b>FIXME: not
	implemented yet.</b>
      </li>
-->

      <li>
        <a href="dreme.html"><b>DREME</b></a> finds motifs in DNA and protein sequences. DREME
	finds relatively short motifs, and does a good job of finding
	multiple motifs in short sequences, that may correspond to
	cofactors. DREME is therefore more sensitive than MEME, at the
	expense of failing to find longer motifs.
      </li>

      <li>
	<a href="../tomtom-intro.html"><b>TOMTOM</b></a> compares a given motif
	or motifs with one or more databases of known motifs, and
	provides a list of motifs from the known motifs that most
	closely match each of the given motifs.
      </li>

      <li>
        <a href="ame.html"><b>AME</b></a> finds motifs
	from databases of known motifs, which are over-represented in
	DNA sequences. AME is more sensitive than MEME and DREME in
	the sense of being able to identify motifs down to any given
	threshold of probability but AME cannot find motifs that are
	not already known. The version of AME we use here has fewer
	options than
	that <a href="http://acb.qfab.org/acb/ame/index.html">previously
	described</a>.
      </li>
      </ul>

      <h2>How MEME-ChIP pre-processes your input sequences</h2>

      <p>
        MEME-ChIP pre-processes your input DNA sequences before
	running some of the above tools. For input to the motif discovery
	and enrichment tools (MEME, DREME, AME), any sequences
	that are longer than 100 base-pairs are trimmed evenly to that length.
	All trimmed sequences are input to DREME and AME, but a maximum
	of 600 (randomly chosen) sequences are input to MEME.
      </p>

      <p>
	The output report, which you can see one all the tools have
	completed, lists the commands you could run on the command line
	to reproduce the outputs, and provides pointers to outputs of
	all the above tools. 
      </p>
      <p>
	In addition, the output report makes available the following files:
      </p>
      <ul>
	<li><code>sequences</code> &#8210; your original sequences
	</li>
	<li><code>seqs-centered</code> &#8210; the trimmed versions of your sequences;
	<b>note:</b>any trimmed sequences contain only <code>N</code>s
	(usually due to repeat masking) are discarded by MEME-ChIP 
	</li>
	<li><code>seqs-shuffled</code> &#8210; dinucleotide-shuffled versions of the trimmed sequences,
	  used as a background model for AME
	</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
	In the event that you submit more than 600 sequences, the following
	files are also provided:
      </p>
      <ul>
	<li><code>seqs-sampled</code> &#8210; a random sample of 600 of your input sequences</li>
	<li><code>seqs-discarded</code> &#8210; the remainder of your sequences
	  (not used by MEME-ChIP, but which you could use a a positive control set) </li>
      </ul> 

    </div>
  </body>
</html>
