<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
                      "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd"
>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>mhmms</title>
    <link href="./meme-suite.css" rel="styleSheet" type="text/css" />
  </head>
  <body>
    <div id="main">
      <script src="./meme-suite-logo.js" type="text/javascript">></script>
      <h1>mhmms</h1>
      <p><b>Usage:</b> mhmms [options] &lt;<i>HMM file</i>&gt;
      &lt;<i>FASTA file</i>&gt;</p>
      <p><b>Description:</b></p>
      <p><code>mhmms</code> searches a sequence database using a
      Meta-MEME motif-based hidden Markov model (HMM) of the kind
      produced by <a href="mhmm.html">mhmm</a>. Each sequence in the
      database is assigned an E-value, and the IDs and scores of
      sequences scoring below a given threshold are printed in sorted
      order.</p>
      <p>The E-value of a given sequence is the expected number of
      sequences which match the given model as well or better than this
      sequence that you would expect to see by chance in a random
      database of the same size as the given database. Scores are
      assigned using a local search algorithm; in other words, the
      algorithm finds the subsequence that matches a subset of model
      states with highest log-odds.</p>
      <p>The emission probabilities in the model are converted to
      log-odds scores before performing the local search. This is done by
      combining pseudocount probabilities derived from a score matrix
      (see the '--pam' and '--score-file' options below) with the
      emission frequencies. You can control the relative weight placed on
      the emission probabilities versus the pseudocount probabilities
      (see '--pseudo-weight' below). The adjusted emission probabilities
      are then converted to odds by dividing by background probabilities
      (see '--bg-file' below). Finally, they are converted to log-odds
      scores by taking their logarithm.</p>
      <p>Transition probabilities are converted to log-odds scores by
      taking their logarithms before searching. This can be overridden
      and the gap scores can be set explicitly using the '--gap-open' and
      '--gap-extend' switches, below. This allows you to specify a single
      affine gap cost function for all spacers in the model.</p>
      <p><b>Input:</b></p>
      <ul>
      <li>&lt;<i>HMM file</i>&gt; - An HMM in <a href="mhmm.html">Meta-MEME
      format</a> must be provided. If the filename is given as '-', then
      <code>mhmms</code> will attempt to read the HMM from standard
      input.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>&lt;<i>FASTA file</i>&gt; - <code>mhmms</code> requires a
      sequence database in <a href="fasta-format.html">FASTA format</a>.
      If the filename is given as '-', then <code>mhmms</code> will
      attempt to read the database from standard input.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><b>Output:</b></p>
      <p><!-- START OUTPUT -->
      The <code>mhmms</code> output has up to three sections containing
      your search results:
      </p>
      <ul>
      <li><a href="#search">Database Search Results</a></li>
      <li><a href="#align">Alignments</a></li>
      <li><a href="#diagrams">Motif Diagrams</a></li>
      </ul>
      <p>
      The second two sections will not be present unless the -fancy
      option was specified.
      </p>
      <p>The results in all three sections are sorted by increasing
      E-value if possible, or by decreasing alignment score if E-values
      could not be computed. <a name="search"></a></p>
      <p><b>DATABASE SEARCH RESULTS</b></p>
      <p>The "Database Search Results" section consists of lines of the
      following form:</p>
      <p><code><nobr>&lt;ID&gt; &lt;E-value&gt; &lt;Score&gt;
      &lt;Start&gt; &lt;End&gt; &lt;Length&gt;
      &lt;Description&gt;</nobr></code></p>
      <p>These fields contain, for each alignment,</p>
      <ul>
      <li><b>ID</b> - The sequence identifier, as given in the database
      file.</li>
      <li><b>E-value</b> - The E-value, which is the total number of
      alignments that you would expect with alignment scores as good as
      this alignment if the database contained only sequences unrelated
      to the query. Thus, a small E-value indicates a good
      alignment.</li>
      <li><b>Score</b> - The Viterbi alignment score. The Viterbi
      algorithm finds the (local) path through the model that has the
      highest score with respect to the given database sequence. This
      probability is divided by the probability of the same sequence with
      respect to a simple, zero-order Markov background model. The
      resulting ratio (called the odds score) is converted to a logarithm
      (base 2) and is printed in this column. The Viterbi log-odds score
      is the basis for the E-value score in the previous column.</li>
      <li><b>Start</b> - The position in the sequence where the alignment
      begins.</li>
      <li><b>End</b> - The position in the sequence where the alignment
      ends.</li>
      <li><b>Length</b> - The length of the sequence.</li>
      <li><b>Description</b> - The sequence descriptor. This description
      is taken from the FASTA database file, and is truncated so that the
      output fits easily on one line.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><a name="align"></a></p>
      <p><b>ALIGNMENTS</b></p>
      <p>Each alignment lists the sequence identifier, alignment E-value
      and log-odds score along the left. On the right, it shows the
      alignment of the model with the sequence in groups of three
      segments.</p>
      <ul>
      <li>Each segment contains, in the bottom-most line, 50 letters from
      the target database sequence, flanked by that segment's start and
      end locations within the entire sequence. Thus, the first segment
      would be flanked by \"1\" and \"49,\" the second by \"50\" and
      \"99,\" etc.</li>
      <li>Aligned above these 50-letter segments are the motifs in the
      model. The motifs are labeled with numbers in the order they
      appeared in the <code>MEME</code> output file from which the model
      was built. A plus or minus sign preceding a motif indicates that
      the motif occurs on the given (+) or reverse complement (-) of the
      DNA sequence in the database. Each position within a motif region
      is indicated by a letter, and each gap position is indicated with a
      period.</li>
      <li>In between the sequence segment and the corresponding model
      positions is a line that indicates the degree of match between the
      motifs and the sequence. If the letter in the motif with the
      largest log-odds score appears in the sequence, then the match row
      contains that letter. If the sequence letter does not have the
      largest log-odds score, but does have a positive log-odds score,
      then the match row contains a plus sign. Otherwise, the match row
      is empty.</li>
      </ul>
      <a name="diagrams"></a>
      <p><b>MOTIF DIAGRAMS</b></p>
      <p>The motif diagrams section shows the alignments in schematic
      format. For each alignment, in the right two columns, it shows the
      sequence identifier and the alignment E-value. On the left, it
      shows the positions and spacings of the motifs in the alignment.
      Hits are labeled with numbers corresponding to the order the motifs
      were given in the query. A plus or minus sign preceding a motif
      indicates that the motif occurs on the given (+) or reverse
      complement (-) of the DNA sequence in the database. 
      <!-- END COPY --></p>
      <p><b>LOG-ODDS SCORES</b></p>
      <p>The log-odds scores for each motif column are created using
      prior information on the letters appearing in alignment columns.
      The prior information is the target frequencies [Karlin,S. and
      Altschul,S.F., PNAS USA , 87, 2264-2268] implicit in a scoring
      matrix. Meta-MEME can read a user-specified scoring matrix (in the
      same format as used by the BLAST family of programs) from a file or
      generate a PAM matrix. By default, PAM 250 is used for proteins,
      and PAM 1 is used for DNA. For DNA, the "PAM 1" frequency matrix
      is</p>
      <pre>
              .990 .002 .006 .002
              .002 .990 .002 .006 
              .060 .002 .990 .020
              .020 .060 .002 .990
      </pre>
      <p>Meta-MEME calculates the target frequencies q<sub>ij</sub> =
      p<sub>i</sub>p<sub>j</sub> exp(L s<sub>ij</sub>) from the scoring
      matrix s<sub>ij</sub> and the background letter frequencies
      p<sub>i</sub> by finding the value of L that makes the
      q<sub>ij</sub> sum to one. These target frequencies are then used
      to create pseudo-frequencies to be added to the emission
      frequencies of the column, following the approach of [Henikoff,S.
      and Henikoff,J.G., JMB, 243, 574-578]. The pseudo-frequency for the
      i<sup>th</sup> letter is computed as: g<sub>i</sub> = sum <sub>j in
      alphabet</sub> (f<sub>j</sub> q<sub>ij</sub>/p<sub>j</sub>).</p>
      <p>The pseudo-frequencies, g<sub>i</sub>, are then combined with
      the emission frequencies, f<sub>i</sub> to give frequency
      estimates</p>
      <center>Q<sub>i</sub> = (alpha f<sub>i</sub> + beta g<sub>i</sub>)
      / (alpha + beta).</center>
      <p>
      In general, alpha should be proportional to the amount of
      independent information in the emission frequencies. We have set it
      to the constant 20. The parameter beta is arbitrary and controls
      the relative importance of prior information. We set it to the
      constant 10.
      </p>
      <p>Our method is essentially that used in PSI-BLAST [Altschul,S.F
      et al., NAR, 25:17, 3389-3402] without</p>
      <ol>
      <li>sequence weighting, and</li>
      <li>scaling for amount of independent information (alpha).</li>
      </ol>
      <p>
      To do 1) and 2) correctly would require having and using alignment
      information rather than emission frequencies as the starting
      point.</p>
      <p><b>Options:</b></p>
      <ul>
      <li>--paths single|all - This option determines how
      <code>mhmms</code> computes raw scores. With the
      <code>single</code> option, <code>mhmms</code> computes the Viterbi
      score, which is the log-odds score associated with the single most
      likely match between the sequence and the model. The
      <code>all</code> option yields the total log-odds score, which is
      the sum of the log-odds of all sequence-to-model matches. The
      default is Viterbi scoring.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--p-thresh &lt;p-value threshold&gt; - The '--p-thresh' switch
      activates p-value score mode with the given threshold. (The default
      score mode is called "log-odds score mode".) In p-value score mode,
      motif match scores are converted to their p-values. They are then
      converted to bit scores as follows:
      <div style="margin-left: 2em">S = -log<sub>2</sub>(p/T)</div>
      where S is the bit score of the hit, p is the p-value of the
      log-odds score, and T is the p-value threshold. In this way, only
      hits more significant than the p-value threshold get positive
      scores. The p-value threshold, T, must be in the range
      0&lt;T&lt;=1. This mode of scoring automatically activates the
      '-motif-scoring' feature (described below under "Advanced
      Options:") so that partial motif hits are disallowed.
      <p><b>Note</b>:</p>
      <ul>
      <li>If <em>p-value threshold</em> is too small, there may be few
      (or no) "hits", and, consequently, few (or no) matches. This may
      cause <code>mhmms</code> to be unable to compute match E-values, or
      to report no matches. Small values of the <em>p-value
      threshold</em> may also cause the reported E-values to be
      inaccurate. In this case, the E-values will always be too large
      (conservative). The proper value for the <em>p-value threshold</em>
      can only be determined by experimentation since it depends on the
      number of motifs, the information content of the motifs and the
      value of <em>maxgap</em>.</li>
      </ul>
      </li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--both-strands - This allows matches to occur on either DNA
      strand. By default, motif matches are only on the given strand. The
      -both-strand switch implies the motif-scoring switch.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--e-thresh &lt;<i>threshold</i>&gt; - <code>mhmms</code> lists
      the sequences that have E-values below the given threshold. The
      default threshold is 10.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--fancy - The '--fancy' switch turns on a more detailed output
      format that shows, in addition to the score for each sequence, the
      complete model-to-sequence match. Here is an example of the fancy
      output format, showing a two-motif model matching a sequence of
      length 179:</li>
      <li style="list-style: none">
      <pre>
                         *.................................................
                                                                           
        170K_TRVPS     1  GAHLVPTKSGDADTYNANSDRTLCALLSELPLEKAVMVTYGGDDSLIAF    49

                         .........................FDWqKFAGtWH..............
                                                   D+  F G+                
        170K_TRVPS    50 PRGTQFVDPCPKLATKWNFECKIFKYDVPMFCGKFLLKTSSCYEFVPDPV    99

                         ..................................................
                                                                           
        170K_TRVPS   100 KVLTKLGKKSIKDVQHLAEIYISLNDSNRALGNYMVVSKLSESVSDRYLY   149

                         ......GYCPEVKPI...............*
                                 C+  K I                
        170K_TRVPS   150 KGDSVHALCALWKHIKSFTALCTLLPRRKG    179
      </pre></li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--width &lt;<i>int</i>&gt; - Specify the width (in characters)
      of each line in the output. The description of each sequence, which
      is taken from the input FASTA file, will be truncated as necessary.
      By default, the output width is 132 characters.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--nosort - Do not sort the output.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--bg-file &lt;<i>file</i>&gt; - This switch allows you to
      specify a different background letter distribution. The background
      letter distribution is used in converting the emission
      probabilities in the model to log-odds. By default, the background
      letter distribution of the appropriate (DNA or protein) NCBI
      non-redundant database is used. With the '--bg-file' switch, the
      background distribution is read from a file whose format is the
      same as used by MEME and MAST. The file must contain one line for
      each letter in the (unambiguous) character set. Each line must
      contain the letter followed by the letter's frequency. All other
      lines in the file are ignored, including comment lines starting
      with '#'. For example, <em>file</em> might contain:
      <pre>
# tuple   frequency_non_coding
      a       0.324
      c       0.176
      g       0.176
      t       0.324
      </pre>
      (You can produce a file in the proper format from any FASTA
      sequence file (DNA or protein) using the fasta-get-markov utility,
      which is included with the Meta-MEME distribution in directory /bin.
      Type fasta-get-markov &lt; f.fasta &gt; f.bg to make a file named
      "f.bg" containing the letter distribution from FASTA file
      "f.fasta". )</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--allow-weak-motifs - In p-value score mode, weak motifs are
      defined as ones where the best possible hit has a p-value less than
      the p-value threshold. Such motifs cannot contribute to a match in
      p-value score mode. By default, <code>mhmmscan</code> rejects any
      search containing weak motifs, unless the -allow-weak-motifs switch
      is given. In that case, the search will proceed, but the weak
      motifs will never appear in any matches. <b>Note</b>:This switch
      only applies to p-value score mode.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--progress &lt;value&gt; - Print to standard error a progress
      message after every <i>value</i> sequences.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--verbosity 1|2|3|4|5 - Set the verbosity level of the output
      to stderr. The default level is 2.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--noheader - Do not put a header on the output file.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--noparams - Do not list the parameters at the end of the
      output.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--notime - Do not print the running time and host name at the
      end of the output.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--quiet - Combine the previous three flags and set verbosity to
      1.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><b>Advanced Options:</b></p>
      <ul>
      <li>--zselo - Specifying the '--zselo' switch causes the spacer
      emission log-odds scores to be set to zero. This prevents regions
      of unusual base/residue composition matching spacers well when the
      spacer emission frequencies are different than the background
      frequencies. It is particularly useful with DNA models.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--gap-open &lt;<i>cost</i>&gt; - The '--gap-open' switch causes
      <b>all</b> transitions into a spacer state to be assigned a
      log-odds score equal to <em>-cost</em>. Together with the
      '--gap-extend' switch, this allows you to specify an affine gap
      penalty function, overriding the gap penalty implicit in the model
      (transition probabilities into and out of gap states).</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--gap-extend &lt;<i>cost</i>&gt; - The '--gap-extend' switch
      causes <b>all</b> spacer self-loop log-odds scores to be set to
      <em>-cost</em>. In addition, it causes all other transitions out of
      a spacer to be set to zero. Together with the '--gap-open' switch,
      this allows you to specify an affine gap penalty function,
      overriding the gap penalty implicit in the model (self-loop
      transition probabilities of gap states).</li>
      </ul>
      <p><i>The following option is automatically invoked when you
      specify --p-thresh. You can also set it when you do not want
      p-value score but want to prevent partial matches to
      motifs.</i></p>
      <ul>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--motif-scoring - This option prevents alignments from
      containing a partial motif.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><i>The following options can be used in both p-value and
      log-odds score modes to control how the emission probabilities in
      the HMM are converted into log-odds scores.</i></p>
      <ul>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--pseudo-weight &lt;<i>weight on pseudocounts</i>&gt; - By
      default, the pseudocount probabilities are weighted by 10, and
      emission probabilities in the model by 20. The weight on the
      pseudocount probabilities can be adjusted to any value greater than
      or equal to zero using the '--pseudo-weight' switch. The smaller
      the weight, the less effect the pseudocount probabilities have, and
      the closer the adjusted probabilities will be to the emission
      probabilities in the model.</li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--pam &lt;distance&gt; - By default, target probabilities are
      derived from the <em>distance-250</em> PAM matrix for proteins, and
      from a <em>distance-1</em> transition/transversion matrix for DNA.
      With the '-pam' switch, you can specify a different <b>integer</b>
      distance from 1 to 500. (This can be overridden with the
      '--score-file' switch, below). The <em>distance-1</em>
      transition/transversion joint probability matrix for DNA is given
      below:
      <pre>
             A    C    G    T    
        A  .990 .002 .006 .002
        C  .002 .990 .002 .006
        G  .006 .002 .990 .002
        T  .002 .006 .002 .990
      </pre></li>
      <li style="list-style: none"></li>
      <li>--score-file &lt;<i>score file</i>&gt; - The '--score-file'
      switch causes a score file (in BLAST format) to be read and used
      instead of the built-in PAM (for proteins) or
      transition/transversion (for DNA) score file. Several score files
      are provided (including BLOSUM62) in directory mhmm/data. Other,
      user-provided score files may be specified as well, as long as they
      are in the proper format.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><b>Bugs:</b> None known.</p>
      <p>Author: <a href="http://www.gs.washington.edu/~noble">William
      Stafford Noble</a>.</p>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
