<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
                      "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd"
>
<html>
  <head>
    <title>GOMO - a Gene Ontology association tool for motifs</title>
    <link href="./meme-suite.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" />
  </head>
  <body>
    <div id="main">
      <script src="./meme-suite-logo.js" type="text/javascript">></script>
      <img src="images/gomo_logo.png" alt="GOMO logo" />
      <p><b>Usage:</b><br />
      <code>gomo [options] &lt;go-term database&gt; &lt;scoring file&gt;+</code>
      </p>
      <p><b>Description:</b><br />
      The name <code>GOMO</code> stands for "Gene Ontology for Motifs."  
      The program searches in a set of ranked genes for enriched GO terms
      associated with high ranking genes. The genes can be ranked, for example,
      by applying a motif scoring algorithms on their upstream sequence.
      
      The p-values for each GO-term are computed empirically by shuffling 
      the gene identifiers in the ranking (ensuring consistancy across species) to 
      generate scores from the null hypothesis. Then q-values are derived from
      these p-values following the method of Benjamini and Hochberg 
      (where "q-value" is defined as the minimal false discovery rate at which 
      a given GO-term is deemed significant).
    
      The program reports all GO terms that receive q-values smaller than a 
      specified threshold, outputting a gomo score with emprically calculated 
      p-values and q-values for each.
      </p>

      <p><b>Input:</b></p> 
      <ul> 
      <li>
      <code>&lt;go-term database&gt;</code> is a collection of GO terms mapped to
      to the sequences in the scoring file. Database are provided by the 
      webservices and are formated using a simple tsv-format:<br />
      <i>"GO-term" "Sequence identifiers separated by tabulator"</i> <br />
      The exception to this rule is the first line which instead contains the 
      url to lookup the gene ids. The url has ampersands (&amp;) replaced with
      &amp;amp; and the place for the gene id marked by the token "!!GENEID!!" .
      </li>
      <li>
      <code>&lt;scoring file&gt;</code> is a XML file which contains for each 
      motif the sequences and their score. The XML file uses the 
      <a href="http://zlab.bu.edu/~phaverty/SupplementalData/CisML">CisML</a>
      schema. When scoring data is available for multiple related species 
      <code>GOMO</code> can take multiple scoring files where the true sequence 
      identifiers have been mapped to their orthologs in the reference species
      for which the go-term database was supplied.
      </li>
      </ul>
      
      <p><b>Output:</b></p>
      <p>
      GOMO will create a directory, named <code>gomo_out</code> by default.
      Any existing output files in the directory will be overwritten.
      The directory will contain:
      </p>
      <ul>
      <li>
      An XML file named <code>gomo.xml</code> providing the results in a machine readable <a href="gomo-format.html" >format</a>.
      </li>
      <li>
      An HTML file named <code>gomo.html</code> providing the results in a human readable format.
      </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        The default output directory can be overridden using the <code>--o</code> or <code>--oc</code>
        options which are described below. <br />
        <br />
        Additionally the user can override the creation of files altogether
        by specifying the <code>--text</code> option which outputs to standard out in a tab seperated values
        format:<br />
        "Motif Identifier" "GO Term Identifier" "GOMO Score" "p-value" "q-value"<br />
      </p>
      <p>
      By default GOMO calculates the ranksum statistics on the <i>p</i>-values 
      of each gene given in the 
      <a href="http://zlab.bu.edu/~phaverty/SupplementalData/CisML">CisML</a> 
      input file . 
      Using the option <code>--gs</code> switches
      the focus from the <i>p</i>-values to the scores. 
      Any sequence failing to provide a <i>p</i>-value will prompt GOMO to abort
      the calculations. The same happens when any of the genes in the CisML file
      lacks a score attribute and <code>--gs</code> was activated. 
      </p>
      <p>
      <b>Options:</b> 
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li><command-option name="o"/></li>
        <li><command-option name="oc"/></li>
        <li><command-option program="gomo" name="dag"/></li>
        <li><command-option program="gomo" name="text"/></li>
        <li><command-option name="motif"/></li>
        <li><command-option program="gomo" name="shuffle_scores"/></li>
        <li><command-option program="gomo" name="score_E_thresh"/></li>
        <li><command-option program="gomo" name="t"/></li>
        <li><command-option program="gomo" name="min_gene_count" /></li>
        <li><command-option program="gomo" name="gs"/></li>
        <li><command-option name="nostatus"/></li>
        <li><command-option name="verbosity"/></li>
      </ul>
    </div>
  </body>
</html>
